<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Pirates | The Blog from Darel]]></title>
  <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/categories/pirates/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://darelf.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-22T14:12:27-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://darelf.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Darel Finkbeiner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lazarus - Yo Ho]]></title>
    <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/04/14/lazarus-yo-ho/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-14T12:32:30-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/04/14/lazarus-yo-ho</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Life no longer gives me lemons. Not after what happened the last time.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>There had been an agreement made to help hunt down and defeat one of the
pirate captains. This was in exchange for the location of a buried treasure.
Partly completed, I think, because Captain <del>Mars</del> Deeds thought
that the treasure itself is actually a myth. Or at least that it&rsquo;s impossible
to get at it.</p>

<p>So we all truck out in pursuit of this guy&rsquo;s pirate ship. A short bit of naval
maneuvering goes on while some fire is exchanged, and eventually we latch on
and can head across to the enemy ship.</p>

<p>This may be my first experience with this group where entrance into the battle
happened exactly as planned. Bravo.</p>

<p>We quickly set up a permieter of fighters, with our mage and archer protected.
An enemy archer distracted for a short time such that we couldn&rsquo;t bring the
full force of our long range attack on the foot soldiers.</p>

<p>However, the battle quickly evolved as the enemy brought in air support and
additional reinforcements. Our bubble of steel pushed out a bit to try and
reduce the enemies area effect attacks, and we slowly chewed through them.
I spent my time dashing around the battle field, distracting enemy troops,
dispensing the blessings of Calistria, healing, and basically being a
nuisance to the foe.</p>

<p>The tide began to turn, and I unleashed my fury upon the enemy archer. She
was delicious. At that point, with the enemy in full retreat, our soldiers
managed to prevent the leader from escaping. While he tried to surrender like
a little baby, the warriors were having none of it and despatched him quickly.</p>

<p>Having secured the location of the treasure, and having finally tasted the
fruits of working in concert, we are prepared to face whatever dangers are
guarding the lost treasure of Angus.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
