<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Culture | The Blog from Darel]]></title>
  <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/categories/culture/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://darelf.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-22T15:31:52-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://darelf.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Darel Finkbeiner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Programmer Identification]]></title>
    <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/02/04/programmer-identification/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-04T07:47:45-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/02/04/programmer-identification</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Seems like people are complicated creatures. Sure. But we always seem to come back
to certain variables that we all latch on to when trying to identify each other
or to predict behavior. Gender, race, social class, politics, hobbies, etc.
<!--more-->
For the most part, these work as pretty good predictors, you can almost always tell
“if X then Y” and make fairly accurate generalizations.</p>

<p>We do this for a lot of reasons, but one is to find those that we would be
compatible with. In fact, a lot of the identifiers that we look for are usually
in relation to our own preferences and not some objective standard. So while, for
instance gender is an objective identifier, something like “goes to Starbucks a lot”
would be just as useful as an indentifier for social compatibility.</p>

<p>So, how do programmers/software engineers/developers identify possible compatibilities?
Outside of the standard ones, such as “wears sandles at all times” or “drives a Prius”
or “deeply and passionately believes that proper government can solve problems”, we
have to look at preferences that indicate something about that person.</p>

<p>Since, as I mentioned, this is kind of subjective, I will only be talking about things
that matter to me even in the smallest way, along with how important or useful an
indicator it is with “1” being not very useful at all, and “10” being apocalyptic.</p>

<h4 id="tabs-or-spaces---2">Tabs or Spaces - 2</h4>
<p>Spaces is the correct answer here.</p>

<p>Why so high as a 2? Well, there are two indications here. The first is that if you are
the kind of programmer who has never really considered which one is better and has
experimented with both to find what’s right for you, then that’s an indicator that we
probably don’t have much in common. In fact, that would be an even bigger negative
than choosing Tabs.</p>

<h4 id="functional-language---5">Functional Language - 5</h4>
<p>There are two main camps of good programmers. (I mean good in the sense of “good at
their job”). The ones who like math, and the rest of us.</p>

<p>I am not a mathemetician. I passed my classes, but have forgotten everything past
Algebra since I never use any of it in my line of work. This means that I generally
hate things like Lisp. And I’ve tried Lisp and Erlang and Scala and Haskell and others,
but just never got into them.</p>

<p>As xkcd once remarked they have “the flexibility and power of abstract mathematics
with the intuitive clarity of abstract mathematics”. Which is why I generally just
stay away from “functional” languages. I understand, by the way, why it’s called that
but I have a hard time viewing those languages as functional in the normal sense
of the word.</p>

<h4 id="command-line-or-ide---7">Command Line or IDE - 7</h4>
<p>This is a tough one, since in some circumstances an IDE is the most efficient.
But to make it a seven it has to be a preference for an IDE over command line, where
all other things are equal. That is, when editing HTML, you prefer Eclipse over Vi,
in which case we will just never get along.</p>

<p>When I bring new people in at work, we go over how to build the projects both at
the command line and using the Eclipse IDE. I lie to them and say it doesn’t matter
and use whatever you want. In reality, it does matter, and if they choose and
stick with the IDE, we generally don’t end up doing a lot of successful projects
together.</p>

<h4 id="single-language---10">Single Language - 10</h4>
<p>This is a ten because if you only program in one language, then I wouldn’t even
call you a programmer. As far as I’m concerned, you chose the wrong profession.</p>

<p>So….</p>

<p>This is just my brief list, and isn’t everything, and reflects my own biases.
Yet, we all use these kinds of things to varying degress to help us match up with
fellow programmers. Maybe one day we can come up with a system for helping match
programmers.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
