<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Writing | The Blog from Darel]]></title>
  <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/categories/writing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://darelf.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-24T10:46:46-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://darelf.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Darel Finkbeiner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exposition]]></title>
    <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/03/24/exposition/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-24T09:29:28-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/03/24/exposition</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There&rsquo;s a very well known saying in writing: &ldquo;Show, Don&rsquo;t Tell&rdquo;</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve read a lot of pro and con on this, and a lot of misunderstanding and overly literal
interpretations of this particular piece of advice. There&rsquo;s a lot of &ldquo;you have to tell
something!&rdquo; kind of response, and the other extreme of &ldquo;only imply!&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Good writing is obvious when you read it. The non-obvious is how good writing happens.
That&rsquo;s where we run into all kinds of problems, and different authors have different little
phrases or mnemonics that help them move their storytelling toward good from wherever they
are.</p>

<p>For instance, Orson Scott Card will tell you that you need exposition. But that&rsquo;s because
he needs to be reminded. Most writers have the exact opposite problem and need to be disciplined
away from excessive exposition. New writers can easily get confused by all the advice, and
end up learning all the wrong things. And then, once habits become ingrained you end up with
a decent writer who has a huge hole that brackets out any chance for greatness. (I&rsquo;m looking
at you George R.R. Martin)</p>

<p>So in the famous screenwriter aphorism &ldquo;exposition = death&rdquo;, what is it about that bit of
advice that we can glean? What does &ldquo;exposition&rdquo; even mean in the context of &ldquo;show, don&rsquo;t tell&rdquo;
that will help lead us to better storytelling (whether novels or screenwriting or whatever)?</p>

<p>First, a nice definition of exposition: &ldquo;a comprehensive explanation&rdquo;. Now, for many people
that&rsquo;s really all you need to know in order to understand why you ought to never use exposition.
But, we&rsquo;ll go a little further. (BTW, this article is exposition)</p>

<p>So what about &ldquo;comprehensive explanation&rdquo; means bad storytelling? Any time every thing about
a character, place, event, etc. is thoroughly explained, you have two of deadliest poisons
to storytelling: boredom and lack of mystery. Hemingway&rsquo;s famous &ldquo;Iceberg Theory&rdquo; captures this
concept, where the bulk is &ldquo;below the water line&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Most importantly, a lack of mystery means you have left nothing to the reader/audience. You
despise them. You think they are stupid. You are being an arrogant prick. Exposition is for
learning, classrooms, sermons, etc. it is not for storytelling. When you explain something in
detail you have taken all the story out of the storytelling; now you&rsquo;re just telling.</p>

<p>For serial entertainment, you have just killed your story. In a TV show, since we now know
everything about a character the show is over. We know everything about the main background of
the setting, there&rsquo;s nothing left. Anything you do now will be boring, since there is nothing
new or interesting, there&rsquo;s no real mystery, no revelation is now possible since you have
just told us everything.</p>

<p>In a movie, you have not only foreclosed on sequels, you have delivered what will be termed
by the audience &ldquo;unsatisfying&rdquo;, &ldquo;disappointing&rdquo;, &ldquo;worst ending ever&rdquo;. There&rsquo;s nothing left,
meaning the audience can take nothing with them; it&rsquo;s all left at the theatre. Another word:
&ldquo;unmemorable&rdquo;. There&rsquo;s nothing for you to think on, so the story will quickly be forgotten.</p>

<p>If you want to write boring, forgettable, cliche driven stories it&rsquo;s very easy. Just have
the characters and setting be comprehensively explained. No matter how deep the characters
are, if they are fully understood by the audience they will be regarded as &ldquo;shallow&rdquo;. When there
is no mystery left, everyone is bored, and everyone will move on and stop thinking about it,
and you and your writing will be forgotten. Which is justice.</p>

<p>The universe hates exposition.</p>

<p>This is not to say that there should never be any &ldquo;telling&rdquo;. But an explanation is not an
exposition. If you give a bit of background information well, you are not giving exposition
though you are certainly &ldquo;telling&rdquo; part of the story in order to give context. That kind of
telling is perfectly normal, and part of regular dialogue in real life as well, so it comes
across as natural.</p>

<p>You will know when you have done the storytelling around a character correctly when discussions
about the &ldquo;true motives&rdquo; or &ldquo;what was that event all about&rdquo; pop up. When the audience has
many different takes on what the expository meaning of the story is, then you know you
haven&rsquo;t given too much away.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
