<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Rpg | The Blog from Darel]]></title>
  <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/categories/rpg/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://darelf.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-22T14:28:06-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://darelf.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Darel Finkbeiner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lazarus - Yo Ho]]></title>
    <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/04/14/lazarus-yo-ho/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-14T12:32:30-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/04/14/lazarus-yo-ho</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Life no longer gives me lemons. Not after what happened the last time.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>There had been an agreement made to help hunt down and defeat one of the
pirate captains. This was in exchange for the location of a buried treasure.
Partly completed, I think, because Captain <del>Mars</del> Deeds thought
that the treasure itself is actually a myth. Or at least that it&rsquo;s impossible
to get at it.</p>

<p>So we all truck out in pursuit of this guy&rsquo;s pirate ship. A short bit of naval
maneuvering goes on while some fire is exchanged, and eventually we latch on
and can head across to the enemy ship.</p>

<p>This may be my first experience with this group where entrance into the battle
happened exactly as planned. Bravo.</p>

<p>We quickly set up a permieter of fighters, with our mage and archer protected.
An enemy archer distracted for a short time such that we couldn&rsquo;t bring the
full force of our long range attack on the foot soldiers.</p>

<p>However, the battle quickly evolved as the enemy brought in air support and
additional reinforcements. Our bubble of steel pushed out a bit to try and
reduce the enemies area effect attacks, and we slowly chewed through them.
I spent my time dashing around the battle field, distracting enemy troops,
dispensing the blessings of Calistria, healing, and basically being a
nuisance to the foe.</p>

<p>The tide began to turn, and I unleashed my fury upon the enemy archer. She
was delicious. At that point, with the enemy in full retreat, our soldiers
managed to prevent the leader from escaping. While he tried to surrender like
a little baby, the warriors were having none of it and despatched him quickly.</p>

<p>Having secured the location of the treasure, and having finally tasted the
fruits of working in concert, we are prepared to face whatever dangers are
guarding the lost treasure of Angus.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lazarus - Business]]></title>
    <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/03/10/lazarus-business/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-10T08:06:49-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/03/10/lazarus-business</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There tends to be, in my experience, a certain bonding moment that
happens among a give group of adventurers. And it usually has to do with loot.
Whether gold or precious gems or magic swords.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Once someone has shown they can bring the loot, and are willing and eager to
share the loot, many of their minor character flaws are suddenly overlooked.
Suddenly, they see the healing and the support in a new light. Suddenly all
of that now has a context. And that context is loot.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s good that we retrieved the hold relic. I&rsquo;ll get some brownie points, Mae
and her band of adventurers will get paid.</p>

<p>Everyone seemed very excited about the dragon we met. More than you would
normally expect from a band of seasoned adventurers. It&rsquo;s almost like they are on some
quest looking for a dragon, though this one turned out not to be what they
were looking for. It was a fun ride, I must admit. Seeing the dragon get at
all those dark dwarves was satisfying.</p>

<p>The drow are just as touchy as ever about visitors. Apparently they were
having some sort of picnic in the backyard and we were seen as crashing the
event. You know, we attempted to just quietly walk in, get the relic and walk
out, no fuss. We even went to the trouble to be invisible, and to not be a bother
by going in through the back, avoiding all the hoopla. Paragons of courtesy, we were.</p>

<p>Some people just can&rsquo;t appreciate manners. Which is typical of drow. I mean, really,
sure I did execute a contract on one of them&hellip; that one time. And yes, I
did <em>technically</em> cut out her heart. And it is <em>obviously</em> true that I ate her heart.
And that may or may not have happened in front of her children &mdash; I honestly wasn&rsquo;t
paying a whole lot of attention at that point, can you blame me? &mdash; but,
I mean, what else was I going to do? Not only was I getting paid, this was the
same drow that shortchanged me. The important take away is that if you claim that
there are fourteen potions of cure light wounds, and it turns out there are only
twelve&hellip; I mean, what do you expect is going to happen?</p>

<p>Also, I learned that I hate driders. I had only heard rumors, but the reality
is pretty horrible. At least horrible to face in battle.</p>

<p>Makes me regret not bringing more wine.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
