<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Versioning | The Blog from Darel]]></title>
  <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/categories/versioning/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://darelf.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-28T14:02:34-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://darelf.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Darel Finkbeiner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Semver]]></title>
    <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/02/07/semver/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-07T09:00:27-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/02/07/semver</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Semantic Versioning. Hell yeah.</p>

<p>So here at work we finally settled on a versioning scheme. After literally
years of trying to push versioning in general, and semantic versioning in
particular, we are now implementing.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>What is &ldquo;semantic versioning&rdquo;?</p>

<p>In short, you know those version numbers you see on all those projects
on the internet with version numbers like 1.2.5 or 0.10.21? Yeah. That.</p>

<p>The problem semantic versioning is trying to solve is dependency. Meaning
that an application often depends on other software projects, and those
other software projects often are currently being developed, either to
fix bugs or add features/enhancements.</p>

<p>This can often be referred to as &ldquo;dependency hell&rdquo; since making sure of
which version of what you are using in a project can be a nightmare, taking
into account which set of features you depend on from different projects,
what those projects in turn depend on, etc. You need to distinguish between
a bug fix version increase, a feature add, or API breaking changes. Maybe
a new feature is one you want, or maybe you don&rsquo;t. How do you tell which
version of a project you have?</p>

<p>More importantly, how do you communicate those decisions in the project
you are working on with both the other developers on your team (if any)
and to the consumers of your project?</p>

<p>In comes semver to save the day.</p>

<p>The basic idea of semver is this:  MAJOR.MINOR.PATCH</p>

<p>Additional labels, like &lsquo;-musical&rsquo; or whatever can be added if things get hairy.
But the basic idea should serve.</p>

<p>The MAJOR part of a version is the basic feature set. That is, the API for
every version of that project that starts with the same MAJOR number should
not change. If version 1.0.0 has a function X that takes argument Y, then
that should also be the case for version 1.3.17 and 1.1.5 as well.</p>

<p>The MINOR part of a version are minor changes to the API. Maybe a new
function, or a change to the way a function works. But all of the existing
API at x.0.0 should still be there, even if the actual workings of those
may have changed.</p>

<p>The PATCH part of a version are bug fixes. These should not introduce new
functionality, but rather fix broken or incorrect functionality, or possibly
refactor internal workings without actually changing the input or output
of the functions.</p>

<p>How do we use this at work?</p>

<p>Now this is a specific case, and we are just now moving to use this. The idea
for us is pretty much as described above, however the movement is a little
more deployment specific than it is functionality specific. That is, the
version number, especially the MAJOR and MINOR numbers, will indicate what
deployment level this is at.</p>

<p>So, the MAJOR number will be the &ldquo;this is in production&rdquo; version. This is
the customer facing, being used in real work, version. 1.0.x will be in
production use, 2.0.x will be it&rsquo;s successor, etc.</p>

<p>The MINOR number will be &ldquo;features being tested&rdquo;. So, 1.1.x will NOT be
in production use, but rather will be something that is being tested to
eventually be included in the 2.0.x version.</p>

<p>Again, that&rsquo;s a specific case for us, and not really required by the
semver specification. We find that kind of structure useful for our purposes,
while I&rsquo;m sure your project(s) will have different needs. The main reason
for this kind of versioning is to prevent problems related to what version
of which project is being used in a given context.</p>

<p>For more information on semantic versioning, you can check out their
<a href="http://semver.org">website</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
