<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Node | The Blog from Darel]]></title>
  <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/categories/node/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://darelf.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-26T13:30:19-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://darelf.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Darel Finkbeiner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Browserify and Me]]></title>
    <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/01/27/browserify-and-me/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-27T08:18:54-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/01/27/browserify-and-me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The title might should be &ldquo;Caught between two worlds&rdquo;, but that sounded
really, really pretentious.</p>

<p>So, I had started a project a while back before realizing that something
like browserify existed. I know. I feel like a moron already, don&rsquo;t rub
it in. And even when I started using it I didn&rsquo;t really understand what
it was going to do.</p>

<p>Then, as I got halfway through the project, I realized what was happening
and started doing what I should have done the whole time. So now, the code
for this web application has two completely different approaches that,
while not technically incompatible, make reading and debugging the code
a chore.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s what I learned in this very specific context:</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m trying to use jquery/bootstrap to build a single page web application,
and then using browserify to make a bridge between the client and the node
server. That is, there are modules that run on node, and the application
module is most easily written in node as well. The only problem is how
to communicate between the server and client over what is essentially a
layer on top of websockets.</p>

<p>It turns out, that the cleanest solution to this problem turned out to be
using custom events on DOM elements from the application code, and catching
those events to do the UI parts. That is, some jquery/bootstrap code can
use all of its normal methods and coding style to accomplish the UI
functions, while the node style application code that has been browserified
can simply fire off events without worrying too much about what&rsquo;s going
to happen.</p>

<p>There are some improvements I can make, and will be making, in said
application. Things like passing in the DOM element to the client application
code, and more cleanly setting up the custom javascript DOM events.</p>

<p>All in all, though, stepping through the code again to refactor for all of
this new knowledge makes for better code and I learned a little something
along the way.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tracking Pathfinder]]></title>
    <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/01/24/tracking-pathfinder/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-24T14:35:35-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/01/24/tracking-pathfinder</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Oh boy. Yeah. The Pathfinder RPG.</p>

<p>We play this game pretty relentlessly. Throughout that whole experience, years of slogging through
Pathfinder campaigns, we come across a simple problem: Pathfinder has a LOT of conditional
modifiers. Wow. A LOT.</p>

<p>As of now, we keep a rather complicated sheet of certain precalculated sets of modifiers that
tend to affect the whole group, things like Bless or Haste, and have them all added up so that
play can continue smoothly. Depending on how many casters, and what the current level is, the
number of modifiers &mdash; and more importantly the number of modifiers that clash &mdash; can get crazy.</p>

<p>So, as two of us are programmers by trade, we thought to ourselves &ldquo;We can do this electronically&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Ah, hubris. That&rsquo;s all fine and well, but definition of the problem became a chore in and of
itself. Luckily we could keep defining down until comfortable with the scope, since we were only
out to please ourselves.</p>

<p>And so&hellip; <a href="http://github.com/darelf/bufftracker">bufftracker</a>. There is a companion web product,
though it is not yet finished. Honestly the base project is not yet finished. As I make more
progress I&rsquo;ll be updating it and probably post more on here about it.</p>

<p>Maybe. I dunno. We&rsquo;ll play it by ear.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
