<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Lazarus | The Blog from Darel]]></title>
  <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/categories/lazarus/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://darelf.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-28T13:59:05-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://darelf.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Darel Finkbeiner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lazarus - Intro]]></title>
    <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/02/28/lazarus-intro/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-28T13:39:17-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/02/28/lazarus-intro</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Introducing Lazarus, Devoted to Calistria:</p>

<p><img src="http://imgur.com/YC7jlwg" width="150px"/></p>

<p>Left on a boat to the infamous Black Pearl of the Tropics. My kind of place.
Pirates, women, treasure, pirate women, wild adventure, women. It really has
everything a man could want. And quite a few other things besides.</p>

<p>While not a sea farer myself, I don&rsquo;t mind the trip. Apparently, our valuable
&ldquo;cargo&rdquo; has crashed on the lovely shores of Mediogalti Island and has survived.
Could even be some of her guard is with her, though that&rsquo;s not quite as important.</p>

<p>In fact, I&rsquo;m sure it&rsquo;s almost beside the point. Actually, I&rsquo;d rather be walking
into a &ldquo;long survivor&rdquo; situation and be the knight to rescue the exceedingly
appreciative damsel in stereotypical distress. Nevertheless, if any of her
barely qualified personal guard has survived, I suppose that would be fine.</p>

<p>This promises to be an exciting mission. In fact, I&rsquo;ve been given permission
from Meron to charter an expedition for one of our lost relics that is
reportedly on the island. Two birds, as it were. Though hopefully there are
many more birds available as well. I might have to requistion some guides
from the wilderness whatever-they-call-themselves, but I have some amount
of funds from the temple to help offset any costs.</p>

<p>If only my favorite treasure hunter was available. It&rsquo;s really too bad
about the guild. She would have loved to go on this expedition, since I&rsquo;m
sure the payout would be plenty to cover her losses back in Sargava.
Unfortunately, I haven&rsquo;t been able to find her. Oh well, more for me then.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
