<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Lazarus | The Blog from Darel]]></title>
  <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/categories/lazarus/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://darelf.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-09T13:43:05-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://darelf.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Darel Finkbeiner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lazarus - Tactics]]></title>
    <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/04/07/lazarus-tactics/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-07T09:01:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/04/07/lazarus-tactics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There&rsquo;s some sort of northern barbarian that hangs out in Mae&rsquo;s group. Odd fellow.
Keeps to himself mostly. At first I thought he didn&rsquo;t speak the language, until
he went into a semi-furious rant about some vision he had.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Unfortunately, the vision was of the assassin cult of Norgorber. Those guys. You
know, one of the groups that if you leave them alone they usually leave you alone.
But apparently, this Pike (or Pickaxe, maybe?) fellow crossed them somehow, or maybe someone put out a
contract on him (though I hadn&rsquo;t heard about it). Whatever the reason, he was in
deep, and these assassins are pretty sneaky; you never know who they are.</p>

<p>We staked out their hideout for a few days until we saw they were having a meeting.
Then we quickly discussed tactics.</p>

<p>Now Mae&rsquo;s guards, the three ex-soldiers, seem to be a little light on tactics.
(That may be why they are &ldquo;ex&rdquo;. That or sleeping on duty seems just as likely)
However, they did manage to have a single stray thought about possible alternate
escape routes for the enemy. But then, instead of actually securing the exit,
instead they sent the pirate Dripstain to take care of it. And he &ldquo;took care of it&rdquo;
by drinking and having a piratey good time, and then watching calmly while several
of the enemy escaped.</p>

<p>When asked, he said something like &ldquo;Oh, you wanted me to stop them? I.. I didn&rsquo;t
know that. I just assumed you wanted me to drink and wench and observe any
of them coming out of the basement. Which I did! Especially the first two items!&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;How many, Dripstain?&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;Oh, maybe three or four. Or maybe it was only one. I was in my fifth cups by
then, and Stacey&rsquo;s ample bosom was blocking some of my view. Plus I was trying to
keep an eye on Jessica, since I thought she might be in on it what with the way
she was swaying her hips at me constantly. Definitely, probably
at least one of the assassins got away.&rdquo; (I&rsquo;m paraphrasing here, but you get the idea)</p>

<p>Meanwhile, with Assisstant Vice Cabin Boy busy, we were laying into the enemy pretty
heavily. Not being a group very good at making our way down corridors, we of course
got completely tangled up just getting into the place, tripping over each other.</p>

<p>Mae got the high ground on some barrels to light up the room with arrow fire.
Eventually we got untangled and went face first into assassins, fire elementals,
and giant scorpians. It was invigorating.</p>

<p>The frustration with the entire affair of just getting in the door made me cranky.
I vaguely remember eating a man&rsquo;s heart. It happens sometimes. After that, of course,
everything is a bit fuzzy since I was high as a kite on lifeblood.</p>

<p>Maybe next time we can have a little better organization on getting through the door.
I know. Baby steps, baby steps.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lazarus - the Not Dead]]></title>
    <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/03/24/lazarus-the-not-dead/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-24T10:56:55-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/03/24/lazarus-the-not-dead</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Having gotten themselves banned from the city, the adventuring group led by Mae approached the
walls with not a little trepidation. Unfortunately, the Red Mantis had a use for the group and
offered to clear their names in exchange for some help. This was obviously not going to play to
my advantage. The Mantis are constantly interfering, the meddlesome brats.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Help from adventuring groups is usually of the &ldquo;kill it until it is dead&rdquo; variety, and this one
was no different. Apparently, the necromantic pirate lady ( I think her name was Necrophilia, or
something? ), had one of her ships occupying the harbor. Who knows why. Certainly for some
nefarious purpose, but which exact type of nefary was unclear.</p>

<p>What was clear, was that a ship full of the not-quite-dead was blocking the harbor from the
wholly legitimate and upright citizens of Ilizmagorti. <em>cue eye roll</em>. So, they bundled us onto
a barge, basically keel-hauling us into doing their dirty work, and so we had not much choice
other than to clear out the undead and sink the ship.</p>

<p>Which brings me to the question of loot. Loot? What loot? I see no loot here. I see no reward for
sinking the ship. I see no upside at all. The pirates should have cleared it out, since they are
the ones for whom the main use and advantage of the harbor is.</p>

<p>Regardless. Dripstain the Pirate God certainly showed his value in sea-going situations. He charged
every enemy, fought from the front and generally energized the entire affair. His pure, piratey
enthusiasm infected the whole group, and everyone got caught up in the Swash and Buckle. It was
a fascinating excursion, from that point of view.</p>

<p>Also, I don&rsquo;t particularly like undead. They are irritating. They suck the souls out of people,
and reduce them to at best wasted husks, and at worst convert them to their undead cause. Which
cause is entirely depressing. I assume most undead are cutters by nature, all sad on themselves,
blaming their parents, etc. If they had hair it would naturally fall in their face and be dyed
black. Whatever. I prefer a more energetic lifestyle.</p>

<p>At least we got to sink a ship by setting it on fire. That&rsquo;s always fun.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lazarus - Business]]></title>
    <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/03/10/lazarus-business/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-10T08:06:49-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/03/10/lazarus-business</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There tends to be, in my experience, a certain bonding moment that
happens among a give group of adventurers. And it usually has to do with loot.
Whether gold or precious gems or magic swords.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Once someone has shown they can bring the loot, and are willing and eager to
share the loot, many of their minor character flaws are suddenly overlooked.
Suddenly, they see the healing and the support in a new light. Suddenly all
of that now has a context. And that context is loot.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s good that we retrieved the hold relic. I&rsquo;ll get some brownie points, Mae
and her band of adventurers will get paid.</p>

<p>Everyone seemed very excited about the dragon we met. More than you would
normally expect from a band of seasoned adventurers. It&rsquo;s almost like they are on some
quest looking for a dragon, though this one turned out not to be what they
were looking for. It was a fun ride, I must admit. Seeing the dragon get at
all those dark dwarves was satisfying.</p>

<p>The drow are just as touchy as ever about visitors. Apparently they were
having some sort of picnic in the backyard and we were seen as crashing the
event. You know, we attempted to just quietly walk in, get the relic and walk
out, no fuss. We even went to the trouble to be invisible, and to not be a bother
by going in through the back, avoiding all the hoopla. Paragons of courtesy, we were.</p>

<p>Some people just can&rsquo;t appreciate manners. Which is typical of drow. I mean, really,
sure I did execute a contract on one of them&hellip; that one time. And yes, I
did <em>technically</em> cut out her heart. And it is <em>obviously</em> true that I ate her heart.
And that may or may not have happened in front of her children &mdash; I honestly wasn&rsquo;t
paying a whole lot of attention at that point, can you blame me? &mdash; but,
I mean, what else was I going to do? Not only was I getting paid, this was the
same drow that shortchanged me. The important take away is that if you claim that
there are fourteen potions of cure light wounds, and it turns out there are only
twelve&hellip; I mean, what do you expect is going to happen?</p>

<p>Also, I learned that I hate driders. I had only heard rumors, but the reality
is pretty horrible. At least horrible to face in battle.</p>

<p>Makes me regret not bringing more wine.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lazarus - New Beginnings]]></title>
    <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/03/03/lazarus-new-beginnings/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-03T08:13:32-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/03/03/lazarus-new-beginnings</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Journal Entry:</p>

<p>Mae is exactly as I remember her. Something about elves, probably.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I convinced her to let me help out on some salvage mission. I don&rsquo;t
even know what they were after. She didn&rsquo;t leave with anything,
which was really odd behavior for her.</p>

<p>She has apparently hired some mercenaries. Fairly sure of themselves.
I haven&rsquo;t seen them prove anything yet, but from the scars and scuff
marks they seem to have experience. Apparently, they are some sort
of local semi-celebrities.</p>

<p>I approve, at any rate. They have gathered up Merideth, and have
somehow conspired to protect her until they return to Sargava.</p>

<p>The after party was interesting, and Mae was completely in her element.
While everyone was discussing what to do about some young girl
that had gotten herself kidnapped, Mae slipped out, saved the
girl, came back and pocketed the reward money. Quest complete.</p>

<p>We were all still eating lunch. Classic.</p>

<p>With Mae&rsquo;s help, I convinced her mercenary friends to help
bring back Merideth and to retrieve that artifact for Meron.
Let&rsquo;s hope some of that muscle can be turned to good use.</p>

<p>Aowyn is still operating in the city. If I didn&rsquo;t have a dozen other
priorities I would do something about that. I still may try to have
Mae acquire one of her poisoned weapons for me, kill Aowyn&rsquo;s associate
with whom she seems to have some animosity, and leave the weapon to
be found with the body. Some guy named &ldquo;Scurvyder&rdquo; or something.</p>

<p>Sitting here in camp with some pervy merc named Marcandus or
Mercurius or something. Just one of those types who at very first
look makes you immediately suspicious. Maybe he&rsquo;ll cozy up to the
camp follower we brought along. Isn&rsquo;t that why we bring them, so
they can satisfy the odd inclination?</p>

<p>Speaking of which, why didn&rsquo;t we think to bring some of the girls
from town? Why does this guy get to bring his own personal boy and
none of the rest of us get anything? This is ridiculous. I only
brought one bottle of wine, too. That&rsquo;s not going to last.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lazarus - Intro]]></title>
    <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/02/28/lazarus-intro/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-28T13:39:17-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/02/28/lazarus-intro</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Introducing Lazarus, Devoted to Calistria:</p>

<p><a href="http://imgur.com/YC7jIwg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/YC7jIwg.jpg" width="150px"/></a></p>

<!--more-->


<p>Left on a boat to the infamous Black Pearl of the Tropics. My kind of place.
Pirates, women, treasure, pirate women, wild adventure, women. It really has
everything a man could want. And quite a few other things besides.</p>

<p>While not a sea farer myself, I don&rsquo;t mind the trip. Apparently, our valuable
&ldquo;cargo&rdquo; has crashed on the lovely shores of Mediogalti Island and has survived.
Could even be some of her guard is with her, though that&rsquo;s not quite as important.</p>

<p>In fact, I&rsquo;m sure it&rsquo;s almost beside the point. Actually, I&rsquo;d rather be walking
into a &ldquo;lone survivor&rdquo; situation and be the knight to rescue the exceedingly
appreciative damsel in stereotypical distress. Nevertheless, if any of her
barely qualified personal guard has survived, I suppose that would be fine.</p>

<p>This promises to be an exciting mission. In fact, I&rsquo;ve been given permission
from Meron to charter an expedition for one of our lost relics that is
reportedly on the island. Two birds, as it were. Though hopefully there are
many more birds available as well. I might have to requistion some guides
from the wilderness whatever-they-call-themselves, but I have some amount
of funds from the temple to help offset any costs.</p>

<p>If only my favorite treasure hunter was available. It&rsquo;s really too bad
about the guild. She would have loved to go on this expedition, since I&rsquo;m
sure the payout would be plenty to cover her losses back in Sargava.
Unfortunately, I haven&rsquo;t been able to find her. Oh well, more for me then.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
