<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Pathfinder | The Blog from Darel]]></title>
  <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/categories/pathfinder/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://darelf.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-10T08:26:36-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://darelf.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Darel Finkbeiner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lazarus - Business]]></title>
    <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/03/10/lazarus-business/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-10T08:06:49-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/03/10/lazarus-business</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There tends to be, in my experience, a certain bonding moment that
happens among a give group of adventurers. And it usually has to do with loot.
Whether gold or precious gems or magic swords.</p>

<p>Once someone has shown they can bring the loot, and are willing and eager to
share the loot, many of their minor character flaws are suddenly overlooked.
Suddenly, they see the healing and the support in a new light. Suddenly all
of that now has a context. And that context is loot.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s good that we retrieved the hold relic. I&rsquo;ll get some brownie points, Mae
and her band of adventurers will get paid. But more importantly, we will have
rescued the future queen, and she will see the hand of Calistria in it. That
kind of good favor goes a long way.</p>

<p>Everyone seemed very excited about the dragon we met. More than you would
normally expect from a band of seasoned adventurers. They might be on some
quest looking for a dragon, though this one turned out not to be what they
were looking for. It was a fun ride, I must admit.</p>

<p>The drow are just as touchy as ever about visitors. Apparently they were
having some sort of picnic in the backyard and we were seen as crashing the
event. You know, we attempted to just quietly walk in, get the relic and walk
out, no fuss. We even went to the trouble to be invisible, and to not be a bother
by going in through the back, avoiding all the hoopla. Paragons of courtesy, we were.</p>

<p>Some people just can&rsquo;t appreciate manners.</p>

<p>Also, I leared that I hate driders. I had only heard rumors, but the reality
is pretty horrible. At least horrible to face in battle.</p>

<p>Makes me regret not bringing more wine.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lazarus - New Beginnings]]></title>
    <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/03/03/lazarus-new-beginnings/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-03T08:13:32-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/03/03/lazarus-new-beginnings</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Journal Entry:</p>

<p>Mae is exactly as I remember her. Something about elves, probably.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I convinced her to let me help out on some salvage mission. I don&rsquo;t
even know what they were after. She didn&rsquo;t leave with anything,
which was really odd behavior for her.</p>

<p>She has apparently hired some mercenaries. Fairly sure of themselves.
I haven&rsquo;t seen them prove anything yet, but from the scars and scuff
marks they seem to have experience. Apparently, they are some sort
of local semi-celebrities.</p>

<p>I approve, at any rate. They have gathered up Merideth, and have
somehow conspired to protect her until they return to Sargava.</p>

<p>The after party was interesting, and Mae was completely in her element.
While everyone was discussing what to do about some young girl
that had gotten herself kidnapped, Mae slipped out, saved the
girl, came back and pocketed the reward money. Quest complete.</p>

<p>We were all still eating lunch. Classic.</p>

<p>With Mae&rsquo;s help, I convinced her mercenary friends to help
bring back Merideth and to retrieve that artifact for Meron.
Let&rsquo;s hope some of that muscle can be turned to good use.</p>

<p>Aowyn is still operating in the city. If I didn&rsquo;t have a dozen other
priorities I would do something about that. I still may try to have
Mae acquire one of her poisoned weapons for me, kill Aowyn&rsquo;s associate
with whom she seems to have some animosity, and leave the weapon to
be found with the body. Some guy named &ldquo;Scurvyder&rdquo; or something.</p>

<p>Sitting here in camp with some pervy merc named Marcandus or
Mercurius or something. Just one of those types who at very first
look makes you immediately suspicious. Maybe he&rsquo;ll cozy up to the
camp follower we brought along. Isn&rsquo;t that why we bring them, so
they can satisfy the odd inclination?</p>

<p>Speaking of which, why didn&rsquo;t we think to bring some of the girls
from town? Why does this guy get to bring his own personal boy and
none of the rest of us get anything? This is ridiculous. I only
brought one bottle of wine, too. That&rsquo;s not going to last.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lazarus - Intro]]></title>
    <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/02/28/lazarus-intro/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-28T13:39:17-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/02/28/lazarus-intro</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Introducing Lazarus, Devoted to Calistria:</p>

<p><a href="http://imgur.com/YC7jIwg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/YC7jIwg.jpg" width="150px"/></a></p>

<!--more-->


<p>Left on a boat to the infamous Black Pearl of the Tropics. My kind of place.
Pirates, women, treasure, pirate women, wild adventure, women. It really has
everything a man could want. And quite a few other things besides.</p>

<p>While not a sea farer myself, I don&rsquo;t mind the trip. Apparently, our valuable
&ldquo;cargo&rdquo; has crashed on the lovely shores of Mediogalti Island and has survived.
Could even be some of her guard is with her, though that&rsquo;s not quite as important.</p>

<p>In fact, I&rsquo;m sure it&rsquo;s almost beside the point. Actually, I&rsquo;d rather be walking
into a &ldquo;lone survivor&rdquo; situation and be the knight to rescue the exceedingly
appreciative damsel in stereotypical distress. Nevertheless, if any of her
barely qualified personal guard has survived, I suppose that would be fine.</p>

<p>This promises to be an exciting mission. In fact, I&rsquo;ve been given permission
from Meron to charter an expedition for one of our lost relics that is
reportedly on the island. Two birds, as it were. Though hopefully there are
many more birds available as well. I might have to requistion some guides
from the wilderness whatever-they-call-themselves, but I have some amount
of funds from the temple to help offset any costs.</p>

<p>If only my favorite treasure hunter was available. It&rsquo;s really too bad
about the guild. She would have loved to go on this expedition, since I&rsquo;m
sure the payout would be plenty to cover her losses back in Sargava.
Unfortunately, I haven&rsquo;t been able to find her. Oh well, more for me then.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tracking Pathfinder]]></title>
    <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/01/24/tracking-pathfinder/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-24T14:35:35-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/01/24/tracking-pathfinder</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Oh boy. Yeah. The Pathfinder RPG.</p>

<p>We play this game pretty relentlessly. Throughout that whole experience, years of slogging through
Pathfinder campaigns, we come across a simple problem: Pathfinder has a LOT of conditional
modifiers. Wow. A LOT.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>As of now, we keep a rather complicated sheet of certain precalculated sets of modifiers that
tend to affect the whole group, things like Bless or Haste, and have them all added up so that
play can continue smoothly. Depending on how many casters, and what the current level is, the
number of modifiers &mdash; and more importantly the number of modifiers that clash &mdash; can get crazy.</p>

<p>So, as two of us are programmers by trade, we thought to ourselves &ldquo;We can do this electronically&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Ah, hubris. That&rsquo;s all fine and well, but definition of the problem became a chore in and of
itself. Luckily we could keep defining down until comfortable with the scope, since we were only
out to please ourselves.</p>

<p>And so&hellip; <a href="http://github.com/darelf/bufftracker">bufftracker</a>. There is a companion web product,
though it is not yet finished. Honestly the base project is not yet finished. As I make more
progress I&rsquo;ll be updating it and probably post more on here about it.</p>

<p>Maybe. I dunno. We&rsquo;ll play it by ear.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
