<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Events | The Blog from Darel]]></title>
  <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/categories/events/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://darelf.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-22T15:31:52-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://darelf.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Darel Finkbeiner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Evented]]></title>
    <link href="http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/04/09/evented/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-09T13:06:49-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://darelf.github.io/blog/2014/04/09/evented</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the big advantages of <a href="http://nodejs.org">node.js</a> is that of events and
an emphasis on asynchronous programming.
<!--more-->
It is almost a given, at this point, that if you learned all your programming
from college, you probably didn’t learn how to write asynchronous functions. In
fact, you were probably warned away from dealing with things that were asynchronous
directly. Instead using pre-packaged frameworks that exposed asynchronous things
( like I/O ) as if they were synchronous, solving your problem for you.</p>

<p>That’s fine. But node.js don’t truck with that.</p>

<p>If you are going to do something in node.js, you need to deal with asynchronous
functions. You need to create functions that can be called asynchronously, and that
play well in that kind of ecosystem. Here are a few tips to help you make the
transition from one to the other.</p>

<p>** Problem - Big File</p>

<p>You have to create many millions of rows of data and output them to a file. You
can’t keep the whole file in memory and write it all at once. You may have infinite
time but you don’t have infinite memory.</p>

<p>Step one is to have a function that creates a row of data.
    function makeOneRow(item) {
      // do something fancy
      return rowOfData
    }</p>

<p>Step two is to create a writable stream. For our purposes, we say a file, so we can
use the <code>fs</code> module.
    var fs = require(‘fs’)
    var outputFile = fs.createWriteableStream(‘name-of-output-file.txt’)</p>

<p>Step three is to loop through your list of items to create and write them to the file
    listOfItems.forEach(function (item) {
      outputFile.write(makeOneRow(item))
    })
    outputFile.end()</p>

<p>“Wait a second!” I hear you exclaim. “What if the makeOneRow() is also asynchronous?”
Maybe the call that makes a row has to call the database, which is almost certainly an
asynchronous call. In this case, we would quickly crash.</p>

<p>One solution to this problem is my favorite: events. The stream functionality that is
available in node.js makes events a natural choice for this. Let’s say for the moment
that creating a row takes a database call that uses a callback.</p>

<pre><code>function databaseCall(item, callback) {
  // do database stuff and store results in processData variable.
  callback(processData)
}
</code></pre>

<p>What do we do with this callback? Well, if we are using events we need a javascript
object that is an <code>EventEmitter</code>. So let’s create one real quick.</p>

<pre><code>var util = require('util')
var events = require('events')

function MyObject() {
  events.EventEmitter.call(this)
}
util.inherits(MyObject, events.EventEmitter)

var myobject = new MyObject()
</code></pre>

<p>Ok. What does this give us? Well, it gives us an object that can call <code>emit</code> in order
to send out events to listeners. So let’s adapt our function that makes items to use it.</p>

<pre><code>MyObject.prototype.makeOneRow = function(item) {
  var self = this
  databaseCall(item, function(processData) {
    self.emit('data', processData)
  })
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now all we have to do is listen for data events and write them to the file. The other
thing is calling only one of these at a time, since we care about the order that
things get written to the file. So when listening for the ‘data’ event, check if
you have more items, and if you do then ask for another one.</p>

<pre><code>function doOne() {
  var nextItem = listOfItems.splice(0,1)
  myobject.makeOneRow(nextItem)
}

myobject.on('data', function(newdata) {
  outputFile.write(newdata)
  if (listOfItems.length &gt; 0) doOne()
})
</code></pre>

<p>Even better would be to allow the object to keep track of how many items, and send
an ‘end’ event when it reached the end. I’ll leave that as an exercise. (You gotta
learn to do it yourself eventually, right?)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
